So now let's just look at a couple of key vocabulary words and a few phrases that we can use for what
所以现在让我们看几个关键词汇和一些短语，我们可以用来做什么
we're going to talk about in this lesson.
我们将在本课中讨论。
So let's start with development.
因此，让我们从开发开始。
Well we talked about progress.
好吧，我们谈到了进展。
That means things are getting better with time moving forward.
这意味着随着时间的推移，事情正在变得更好。
Development can be very similar to progress.
发展可能与进步非常相似。
It's often used in the same way but development can also be related to something just getting maybe
它通常以相同的方式使用，但开发也可能与刚刚获得的东西有关
more mature.
更成熟。
For example when we when we want to explain our personalities when we want to talk about getting older
例如，当我们想要解释我们的个性时，当我们想要谈论变老时
we're talking about maturity and sometimes we're talking about physically getting bigger.
我们谈论的是成熟，有时我们谈论的是身体变大。
So we often call that development but we usually don't call that progress development doesn't always
所以我们经常称之为发展但我们通常不称之为进步发展并不总是
have to be in the direction of it's getting better and better and better not necessarily develop maybe
必须朝着越来越好的方向发展
just means it's getting a little bit more sometimes complicated sometimes more mature.
只是意味着它有时变得更复杂有时更成熟。
Sometimes it's just getting a bit more advanced and it's not always a good thing.
有时它只是变得更先进一点，并不总是一件好事。
But it's very similar development has other meanings as well.
但它非常相似的发展也有其他含义。
But that's the one we're gonna focus on functionality is often used to talk about technology.
但这就是我们要关注的功能，通常用于谈论技术。
We could be talking about gadgets That's a G could be talking about gadgets we could be talking about
我们可能正在谈论小工具 那是一个 G 可能正在谈论我们可能正在谈论的小工具
bigger things like satellites.
更大的东西，比如卫星。
Gadgets are usually smaller but it's often electronic stuff.
小工具通常更小，但通常是电子产品。
And functionality is what those things do.
功能就是这些东西的作用。
So if we're talking about our devices like our cell phones for example or smartphones smartphone is
因此，如果我们谈论我们的设备，例如我们的手机或智能手机，智能手机就是
a phone that can use the Internet maybe has apps.
可以使用互联网的手机可能有应用程序。
If we're going to talk about that.
如果我们要谈这个。
Usually when people review a smartphone or maybe buy one they ask questions about its functionality.
通常，当人们查看智能手机或购买智能手机时，他们会询问有关其功能的问题。
What can it do is basically the meaning of functionality.
它能做什么基本上是功能的意义。
What can this thing do.
这东西能做什么。
And again it's often used for technology if something is very simple very basic.
如果某些东西非常简单非常基本，它也经常用于技术。
Maybe it was useful a long time ago but now there are many many things which are better than it then
也许很久以前它很有用，但现在有很多东西比它更好
we will use the word primitive sometimes primitive can be related to ideas it can be related to people.
我们将使用原始一词，有时原始可以与想法相关，也可以与人相关。
It could be related to traditions primitive traditions.
它可能与传统原始传统有关。
It could be related to technology.
这可能与技术有关。
You could have a technology like a phone from when you were a kid.
你小时候就可以拥有像电话这样的技术。
Right.
正确的。
And that technology seems now very primitive.
而这项技术现在看起来非常原始。
Our smartphones now are very advanced they seem very modern compared to the primitive phones that we
我们的智能手机现在非常先进，与我们使用的原始手机相比，它们看起来非常现代
used to carry around maybe in the 1990s.
过去可能在 1990 年代随身携带。
Now old school is I think a really interesting one.
现在老学校是我认为一个非常有趣的。
Old school is related to the idea of something being kind of classic.
老派与某种经典的想法有关。
And so it's often used in a good way.
所以它经常被很好地使用。
Well that phone is old school.
好吧，那部手机很老派。
If somebody pulls out what's called a flip phone that you flip open it's got a flip phone.
如果有人拿出所谓的翻盖手机，你翻开它就会有翻盖手机。
If somebody takes out a flip phone and says yeah you go Oh that phone is old school.
如果有人拿出翻盖手机说是的，你就去哦，那手机是老派的。
That's not to be too critical.
这不是太挑剔。
It's often to say that's kind of interesting that you have a really old flip phone.
人们经常说你有一部非常旧的翻盖手机很有趣。
Old school old school it's used in sports.
Old school old school 它用于体育运动。
It's used for technology.
它用于技术。
It's used for ideas to use for sometimes fashion old school.
它用于有时用于时尚老派的想法。
It's got nothing to do with school.
跟学校没关系。
Now there are a few phrases we can also use when we're talking about things that happened in the past
现在，当我们谈论过去发生的事情时，我们也可以使用一些短语
which is what we're going to do in this in this lesson we're going to be focusing on past telling a
这就是我们将在本课中要做的事情，我们将专注于过去告诉
story back then is used when you already have said another time.
那时的故事用在你的时候你已经说过另一次了。
So for example in nineteen ninety nine when I was in sixth grade I had a math teacher who was always
例如，在 1999 年，我六年级的时候，我有一个数学老师，他总是
very critical of me.
对我很挑剔。
Back then there was no way for students to give feedback to their teachers.
那时，学生没有办法向老师提供反馈。
So back then it's used once you've already said the time to reference it so that you don't need to say
所以那时候，一旦你已经说过引用它的时间，它就会被使用，这样你就不需要说
that year again or that time again.
那一年还是那一次。
It's often used for a time long ago.
它经常在很久以前使用。
It's not used for usually 20 minutes ago or hours ago or even months ago.
它通常不会在 20 分钟前或几小时前甚至几个月前使用。
It's usually used four years ago way back then.
它通常在四年前使用。
We can also say way back then way back then when I was.
我们也可以说远在那时我在的时候。
So this is a very simple one and we use this one to either talk about our age in a certain time in the
所以这是一个非常简单的，我们用它来谈论我们在某个时间的年龄
past or our status at a certain time in the past when I was 10 years old.
过去或我们在过去某个时间的状态，当时我 10 岁。
You could also say when I was in middle school in middle school and this is a way to again give the
你也可以说当我在中学的时候，这是一种再次给予
person listening to your story a clear idea about the time so that they're able to picture that very
听你故事的人对时间有一个清晰的概念，以便他们能够非常清楚地描绘
well before you say what happened as we talked about in our earlier lesson about description it's very
早在你说出我们在之前的课程中谈到的描述发生的事情之前，
important to give a clear picture to the other person before you actually get into more details or more
在你真正了解更多细节或更多细节之前，给对方一个清晰的画面很重要
complicated things.
复杂的事情。
Now I could only and I could even.
现在我只能而且我什至可以。
These two are very common when we want to talk about limitations and things that are so good that they
当我们想谈论限制和非常好的事情时，这两个是很常见的
have some big advantage that basically the same structure but they have almost opposite meanings.
有一些很大的优势，即基本相同的结构，但它们的含义几乎相反。
If I could say I could only then we're talking about limitation limitation means something you cannot
如果我能说我只能那么我们正在谈论限制限制意味着你不能
do something something cannot do.
做某事不能做的事。
So for example when I was a kid about 12 years old I remember I got a at the time that was called a
因此，例如，当我还是一个大约 12 岁的孩子时，我记得当时我得到了一个叫做 a
flash drive a little card a little USP actually was a USP thumb drive that could only could only store
闪存盘 一个小卡片 一个小 USP 实际上是一个只能存储的 USP 拇指驱动器
about 50 pictures.
大约50张照片。
Now that's unbelievable to think about something that only stores 50 pictures.
现在想想只存储 50 张图片的东西是令人难以置信的。
Back then I could only store 50 pictures or songs in my USP drive today.
那时我只能在我的 USP 驱动器中存储 50 张图片或歌曲。
The USB drive I have can store whole Udemy courses can store much more.
我拥有的 USB 驱动器可以存储整个 Udemy 课程，可以存储更多。
It could only do that back then it was limited.
那时它只能做到这一点，它是有限的。
It could even is pretty much the opposite here.
它甚至可以在这里几乎相反。
If you say it could even do this it's like saying this is good this is good.
如果您说它甚至可以做到这一点，那就像说这很好，这很好。
And wow there's one more which is even better.
哇还有一个更好的。
So let's look at an example or how we could use that and we're often going to be talking about functionality
所以让我们看一个例子或者我们如何使用它，我们经常会谈论功能
for example of technology when we use it could only or it could even I had a slider phone in high school
例如，当我们使用它时只能使用技术，或者它甚至可以在高中时使用滑盖手机
I was going to put H.S. slider phone is a phone that you would slide up and slide down.
我打算把 H.S.滑盖手机是一种可以向上滑动和向下滑动的手机。
Not really a smartphone.
不是真正的智能手机。
OK.
好的。
Now there are many limitations with a smartphone like that.
现在这样的智能手机有很多限制。
Ah sorry.
啊对不起。
A phone like that a phone like that.
那样的电话那样的电话。
So then I could say it was it was really advanced at the time so maybe it compared to phones.
所以我可以说它当时真的很先进，所以也许它与手机相比。
Now it can't do much but at that time.
现在它不能做太多，但在那个时候。
Wow.
哇。
It was really advanced it could do a lot of things should we say it was really progressed.
它真的很先进，如果我们说它真的很先进，它可以做很多事情。
No.
不。
Just to be clear when we talk about that thing the adjective of that thing we say it's very advanced.
只是为了清楚当我们谈论那个东西时，那个东西的形容词我们说它是非常高级的。
Sometimes we say it's very developed although often for a phone for technology we don't use developed
有时我们说它非常发达，尽管通常对于我们不使用的技术的手机来说是发达的
we use developed maybe for language we use it developed for a person we use developed for a topic or
我们使用开发 可能用于语言 我们使用它 开发用于我们使用的人 开发用于主题或
a maybe a a subject.
一个也许是一个主题。
Right.
正确的。
Very developed a country even we could say developed advanced is often for technology.
一个非常发达的国家，甚至我们可以说发达的先进是往往是为了技术。
So I had a slider phone in high school.
所以我在高中时有一部滑盖手机。
It was really advanced at the time.
在当时真的很先进。
It could even or I could even if I said it could even say what it can do if I say I could even.
它甚至可以，或者即使我说它甚至可以说它可以做什么，如果我说我可以。
I'll say what I could do with it I could even listen to music on it.
我会说我能用它做什么我什至可以在上面听音乐。
I could even listen to music on it.
我什至可以在上面听音乐。
What.
什么。
At that time you could listen to music using headphones on a phone.
那时你可以用手机上的耳机听音乐。
Yeah it could even connect to the Internet.
是的，它甚至可以连接到互联网。
What it could connect to the Internet.
它可以连接到互联网。
Yes yes pretty advanced for that time or pretty advanced at the time.
是的，是的，当时相当先进或当时相当先进。
So these words and phrases can be used in many ways.
因此，这些单词和短语可以以多种方式使用。
But the reason I share them is because they are very common as ways to talk about things that happened
但我分享它们的原因是因为它们作为谈论发生的事情的方式非常常见
in the past which improved over time.
过去随着时间的推移而改善。
Things which developed over time things which progressed over time.
随时间发展的事物随时间发展的事物。
And since we're really talking about technology and its progress over time it's important to know these
由于我们真的在谈论技术及其随着时间的推移而取得的进步，因此了解这些很重要
words and phrases.
单词和短语。
So let's now move on and talk about an example or real example of how we can do this how we can tell
所以现在让我们继续讨论我们如何做到这一点的示例或真实示例
a story about the past.
一个关于过去的故事。